<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>…soul, as in software?</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/</link><description>Recent content on …soul, as in software?</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2007-2023 pancho horrillo</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 13:10:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.pancho.name/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Just Discovered OpenVi</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/just-discovered-openvi/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 13:10:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/just-discovered-openvi/</guid><description>Since I moved to NixOS from Arch Linux as my daily driver last year, I missed having traditional vi available on my systems. Having the minimal vi around always felt good, because I could leverage its awesome power (packed in but a couple hundred kilobytes) and snappy startup time to do some edits here and there.
But, alas, it is not available on nixpkgs, and I had not found the time to build it from scratch myself.</description></item><item><title>Yazi is a cool TUI file manager</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/yazi-is-a-cool-tui-file-manager/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2023 12:18:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/yazi-is-a-cool-tui-file-manager/</guid><description>I update my NixOS flake quite often, and usually check the git log of the updated components. Today, when browsing the latest changes to Home Manager, I learned about Yazi, a really cool TUI file manager written in Rust.
If its shell integration is enabled, a shortcut function ya is made available for ease of use.</description></item><item><title>TIL: command -v is the POSIX way to do which</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/command-v-posix-way-to-do-which/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2022 10:58:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/command-v-posix-way-to-do-which/</guid><description>While perusing the password-store git log, I came up with this commit, where I learned that POSIX defines the shell internal command command -v, which behaves like the external command which (that locates the absolute path to an executable, by tracing PATH).
The existence of the internal command (supported by bash, dash and fish, at least) is beneficial for writing more efficient shell scripts.</description></item><item><title>Enabling pinentry in Doom Emacs</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/enabling-pinentry-in-doom-emacs/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 09:26:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/enabling-pinentry-in-doom-emacs/</guid><description>I sometimes use emacs remotely via mosh, and in those situations I cannot depend on the graphical pinentry. Fortunately, the pinentry package (available at GNU ELPA) enables emacs to talk the pinentry protocol, and interface with the gpg-agent directly.
I found useful instructions to set it up under Doom Emacs on its GitHub issue #4647, with minor adjustments:
allow-emacs-pinentry Code Snippet 1: ~/.gnupg/gpg-agent.conf (package! pinentry) Code Snippet 2: ~/.config/doom/packages.el (use-package! pinentry :init (setq epg-pinentry-mode `loopback) (pinentry-start)) Code Snippet 3: ~/.</description></item><item><title>Go: replacing gofmt with gofumpt when using lsp-mode</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/replacing-gofmt-with-gofumpt-when-using-lsp-mode/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 12:55:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/replacing-gofmt-with-gofumpt-when-using-lsp-mode/</guid><description>gofumpt is a better gofmt, with more strictures, that match my personal taste.
It is available at the AUR for Arch linux users as gofumpt.
Add this to your ~/.config/doom/config.el to instruct lsp-mode to use it.
;; https://pkg.go.dev/mvdan.cc/gofumpt ;; https://github.com/emacs-lsp/lsp-mode/blob/8f9259af6fc80a609c2c068d0f59c371205aca89/clients/lsp-go.el#L246 (setq lsp-go-use-gofumpt t) Code Snippet 1: ~/.config/doom/config.el It is directly supported by gopls, it just need to be told to use it.</description></item><item><title>Enabling 4K@60Hz on a RPi 4 on Ubuntu 21.10 Impish Indri</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/enabling-4k60hz-on-a-rpi-4-on-ubuntu-21/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 07:27:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/enabling-4k60hz-on-a-rpi-4-on-ubuntu-21/</guid><description>I have a Raspberry Pi 4 with 8 GiB of RAM, connected to a 4K monitor (Dell U3818DW). Enabling 60 Hz refresh rate should be as easy as adding the hdmi_enable_4kp60=1 flag to /boot/firmware/config.txt.
But there seems to be a problem parsing the EDID information, because the resulting mode only affords 30 Hz.
Fortunately, we can program the mode ourselves:
[pi4] # Enable 4K@60Hz, single monitor #force_turbo=1 disable_fw_kms_setup=1 max_framebuffers=1 hdmi_enable_4kp60=1 hdmi_cvt=3840 1600 60 7 core_freq=600 core_freq_min=600 Code Snippet 1: config.</description></item><item><title>Customizing the default splash screen image on an Intel® NUC8</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/customizing-the-default-splash-screen-image-on-an-intel-nuc8/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 17:12:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/customizing-the-default-splash-screen-image-on-an-intel-nuc8/</guid><description>I have a NUC8i7BEH, which comes by default with some variation of:
Figure 1: The default Intel® NUC logo
Intel® published a way back the Intel® Integrator Toolkit (or ITT for short) which provides an UEFI executable that can be used to replace the default splash image. Let&amp;rsquo;s see how.
Requirements NUC8 or older The list of compatible devices can be found on the download page of the ITT.
A JPEG image with these restrictions: Size At most 60 KB.</description></item><item><title>TIL: The Fisher-Yates Shuffle</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/the-fisher-yates-shuffle/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2021 08:24:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/the-fisher-yates-shuffle/</guid><description>&amp;hellip; or how to efficiently produce a permutation of a set of elements.
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fisher%E2%80%93Yates_shuffle
Incidentally, it is available in math/rand since Go 1.10.
Look for enlightenment here.</description></item><item><title>Preventing systemd – user from launching</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/preventing-systemd-user-from-launching/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 14:40:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/preventing-systemd-user-from-launching/</guid><description>My friend Yari came to me this morning with a small challenge: How to create a temporary user on a GNU/linux system preventing the systemd --user from launching for that user upon login.
According to pam_systemd(8), user@.service is the one running systemd --user
So, we can accomplish what is needed by masking the aforementioned service just before the actual login:
sudo systemctl mask user@.service Now login as the new user to perform some tasks.</description></item><item><title>Backup your CDDA media to a single-file flac with embedded cuesheet</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/cdda-to-single-file-flac/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2019 08:15:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/cdda-to-single-file-flac/</guid><description>On Arch Linux, the required packages are readily available:
abcde flac mkcue abcde -1 -o flac -a default,cue This will produce a couple of files:
A single flac file with an embedded cuesheet (this cuesheet does not include metadata nor track names). A cuesheet file. If you use mpd to listen to your audio, the cuesheet file needs a just a small edit to be usable:
sed -i /^FILE/s/FLAC$/WAVE/ cuesheet.cue</description></item><item><title>Workaround for bad interaction between pipenv and pyenv</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/workaround-for-issue-with-pipenv-pyenv/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 11:58:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/workaround-for-issue-with-pipenv-pyenv/</guid><description>I use Arch Linux these days, and it is a &amp;lsquo;bleeding-edge&amp;rsquo; distro, which means that, typically, only the latest stable versions of upstream packages are available.
Recently, python 3.8 entered the arch repos, replacing python 3.7 altogether. Note that python 2.7 is still available, although I expect that it will be dropped on January.
So, if you are working on a project that depends on python 3.7, you can leverage pyenv, which is readily available from the Community repo.</description></item><item><title>Funny Shell trick</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/funny-shell-trick/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2013 20:17:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/funny-shell-trick/</guid><description>While sorting out a debian .bashrc file, I came across to this construct:
export HISTCONTROL=$HISTCONTROL${HISTCONTROL+,}ignoredups I found interesting the ${HISTCONTROL+,} construct, which will evaluate to a comma (,) if HISTCONTROL is defined, to the empty string otherwise (I checked).
It is useful to enrich (i.e., add while preserving the previous values) variables with new values that must be comma-separated.
I&amp;rsquo;ll try to explain this further.
Let&amp;rsquo;s assume that we have an enviroment variable FOO that controls the behaviour of some program.</description></item><item><title>fork explained Star Wars style, in Perl</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/use-the-fork-luke/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2013 10:32:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/use-the-fork-luke/</guid><description>use Force qw(-midiclorians -jarjar); my $vader = fork; noooooo() unless $vader; # I am your father sub noooooo { hang_there_for_a_while(); exit; # to the Millenium Falcon }</description></item><item><title>Links on Git Workflows</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/links-on-git-workflows/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2011 07:54:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/links-on-git-workflows/</guid><description> http://nvie.com/posts/a-successful-git-branching-model/ http://jeffkreeftmeijer.com/2010/why-arent-you-using-git-flow/ http://www.slideshare.net/sergio.gil/a-git-workflow http://codicesoftware.blogspot.com/2010/11/linus-on-branching.html</description></item><item><title>How to keep a copy of what you watch online</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/keeping-what-you-watch-online/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2009 12:22:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/keeping-what-you-watch-online/</guid><description>Adobe Flash (sic) is so pervasive these days, specially for online video distribution.
Sometimes (e.g., TED.com) the site kindly provides you with a link to download the video stream, but more often than not, they don’t (e.g., YouTube).
There are some tools around which will download the video feed for you, but only work for certain well-known sites. I’m thinking of course of clive and youtube-dl. These tools work by reverse-engineering the protocol the Flash client uses to talk to the &amp;ldquo;mothership&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>Kids, don't try this at home!</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/fork-bombs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2009 17:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/fork-bombs/</guid><description>Look at this beauty:
(){ :|:&amp;amp; };: If fed to bash, it will start a cascade of processes that will leave your box almost inoperable. It is an example of what&amp;rsquo;s called &amp;ldquo;fork bomb&amp;rdquo;. Look there for further discussion, including cure and prevention.
I really love the Perl version of it:
fork while fork he he.
Thanks to my friend Dato for showing it to me!</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Kerberos</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/introduction-to-kerberos/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2009 19:19:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/introduction-to-kerberos/</guid><description>My friend agi referred me to this theatrical introduction to the Kerberos network authentication protocol: Designing an Authentication System: a Dialogue in Four Scenes.
The play portraits two sysadmins working at MIT, Athena and Euripides, who decide to take on the task of designing such a beast.
Really nice reading. Anyone willing to play it?</description></item><item><title>Where was I?</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/where-was-i/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2009 18:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/where-was-i/</guid><description>UNIX® shells maintain the previous working directory in the variable OLDPWD, so it is easy to jump back to where you were previously dwelling:
cd $OLDPWD This is a bit cumbersome to type, so this shortcut is provided:
cd - (My then-classmate Carlos told me about this back in ’98).
Recently I learned that for commands other than cd, which is internal to the shell, ksh and bash provide a tilde expansion for this OLDPWD var, i.</description></item><item><title>Music in the park</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/music-in-the-park/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2009 23:26:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/music-in-the-park/</guid><description>I just came home after a long walk through a park nearby (el Retiro). At a certain point, I started to hear an accordion melody, which I happened to know: « La Valse des monstres » from the Amélie original soundtrack, by Yann Tiersen. This would be no more than a nicety, if it wasn&amp;rsquo;t for the fact that the guy who was playing the melody was also… riding a monocycle!</description></item><item><title>Catalyst on Windows</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/catalyst-on-windows/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2009 16:33:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/catalyst-on-windows/</guid><description>After installing Strawberry Perl run these commands, and may the Gods of ADSL be with you…
C:\&amp;gt; cpanp &amp;#34;s conf prereqs 1; s save&amp;#34; C:\&amp;gt; cpanp &amp;#34;s selfupdate all&amp;#34; C:\&amp;gt; cpanp i Win32::Process Catalyst::Devel</description></item><item><title>Getting X to work on an asus eeebox</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/getting-x-to-work-on-an-asus-eeebox/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2009 10:23:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/getting-x-to-work-on-an-asus-eeebox/</guid><description>Make sure that xorg.conf looks like this:
Section &amp;#34;Device&amp;#34; Identifier &amp;#34;Configured Video Device&amp;#34; Option &amp;#34;monitor-LVDS&amp;#34; &amp;#34;LVDS&amp;#34; EndSection Section &amp;#34;Monitor&amp;#34; Identifier &amp;#34;LVDS&amp;#34; Option &amp;#34;Ignore&amp;#34; &amp;#34;True&amp;#34; EndSection Otherwise, the output will go to the LVDS port, which is not used on the eeebox.
Found the answer here.</description></item><item><title>New url for this blog’s feed - please update your syndication!</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/new-url/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2009 06:25:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/new-url/</guid><description>I’ve reconfigured my site to serve this blog from a static tree, instead of through cgi. The new syndication url is now:
https://blog.pancho.name/index.xml
Please, update your agregator settings to fetch the new url instead of the old one.
I will REMOVE access to the old one in a few days. Thanks!</description></item><item><title>Inspiration</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/inspiration/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2009 11:38:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/inspiration/</guid><description>I just found a reference to this article by Peter Norvig:
Teach Yourself Programming in Ten Years.
Recommended reading.</description></item><item><title>Perl mojo</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/email-purger-in-perl/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2008 09:33:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/email-purger-in-perl/</guid><description>I enjoy writing small Perl scripts to perform admin tasks.
A couple of days ago I had to delete more than 3000 messages in an email inbox, relaying only on POP3 to do it.
Issuing 3000+ dele commands by hand was not a very desirable prospect, so I performed a CPAN search looking for POP3-handling modules.
Bingo! Mail::Box::POP3 does the trick nicely. And it was already installed in my debian box, so I could proceed immediately:</description></item><item><title>Clarke is gone</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/clarke-is-gone/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2008 09:23:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/clarke-is-gone/</guid><description>This morning I started my day watching the 9th episode of &amp;ldquo;The Bing Bang Theory&amp;rdquo;. Just the first minutes, since I had to go to work. It was hilarious, they even made a funny homage to ‘2001 - a space odyssey movie’ (can you believe it?). Feeling comforted by it, I went for my daily dose of slashdot, and then it struck me:
Arthur C. Clarke is dead at 90.</description></item><item><title>Dinosaurs in Madrid!</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/dinosaurs-in-madrid/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2008 15:03:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/dinosaurs-in-madrid/</guid><description>A couple of weeks ago I was taking a pleasant walk by the neighbourhood when… GaLAxY! a Tyrannosaurus rex! Well, not quite, but at least a well preserved craneum from one of them. It was no museum, no… A shop! It is named &amp;ldquo;Geoda&amp;rdquo;, and specializes in fossils and minerals. Must see!
GEODA \ cl. General Díaz Porlier, 19 \ &amp;lt;M&amp;gt; Goya \ Madrid \ SPAIN</description></item><item><title>On ssh-agent</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/ssh-agent/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2008 08:45:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/ssh-agent/</guid><description>Yesterday a friend had an issue with ssh, so after having my dose of sleep, I decided to write about it and share it with the World! :-)
The Problem If you use ssh, you probably have found an use for RSA/DSA keys. With these, instead of having to type (and send) passwords when you connect to a remote host, you just connect! (more on that later).
But unless your private key is saved unprotected (i.</description></item><item><title>Bye bye, pesetas!</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/bye-bye-pesetas/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 May 2007 11:49:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/bye-bye-pesetas/</guid><description>Hoy he ido al Banco de España, a cambiar mis últimas pesetas. Nunca había estado dentro, aunque una vez vi el interior en una película española, con José Coronado (sic).
Me gustó mucho verlo con mis propios ojos, y también fue curioso el proceso de canje; en cierta ventanilla disponen de una máquina donde se echan las monedas, y automáticamente se clasifican y contabilizan, de manera casi instantánea.
Bye bye, pesetas!</description></item><item><title>La Huella de Bach</title><link>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/la-huella-de-bach/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2007 22:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://blog.pancho.name/posts/la-huella-de-bach/</guid><description>Thanks to my friend ANTONIVS, I attended a nice concert today. I enjoyed it thoroughly, except perhaps Hindemith&amp;rsquo;s quartet #5 op. 32, which failed to capture my enthusiasm&amp;hellip; :-)
The last piece of the concert read like this in the booklet:
«Obertura de El holandés errante tal como la tocaría a primera vista una mala orquestina de balneario a las siete de la mañana junto al manantial».
I don&amp;rsquo;t feel very much like translating that one; perhaps one day I will&amp;hellip;</description></item></channel></rss>